<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present aspect of our times and of the extraordinary conjunction of things therein in a rational view and prospect of the same, as it respects the publick hazard and safety of Brittain in this day.</title>
            <author>Fleming, Robert, 1630-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39762</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12111173</idno>
  <idno type="VID">54203</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240935624</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18320</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12111173</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39762)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54203)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 68:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present aspect of our times and of the extraordinary conjunction of things therein in a rational view and prospect of the same, as it respects the publick hazard and safety of Brittain in this day.</title>
                  <author>Fleming, Robert, 1630-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed November 29, 1693"</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Robert Fleming. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54203:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54203:1"/>
            <p>THE Present Aspect OF OUR TIMES, And of the Extraordinary Conjunction Of Things therein.</p>
            <p>In a Rational View and Prospect of the same; As it respects the Publick Hazard and Safety of <hi>Brittain</hi> in this Day.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licensed</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>November</hi> 29. 1693.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurst</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the Lower End of <hi>Cheapside,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:54203:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54203:2"/>
            <head>THE Present Aspect OF OUR TIMES.</head>
            <p>IT is one of the great Trials of Judgment and Prudence, to know when it may be more suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be silent, than to speak: Silence is usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the fafest hand for Men to err on, especially in a Subject of so High, and Publick Concern as this, when so great a variation of Light is unavoidable, amongst Men of the most Judicious Spirits; so that I may say, it hath made it not easie to enter on a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of such a nature: For I know my self to have more cause, to understand Counsels, and Thoughts of others, than to offer what may be mine, in so Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Age as this: But since the Integrity of a Design is in any case, a special Support; and that I may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, it is under no Private Influence or Engagements, I have exposed this to the Publick View; I shall offer no other Apology but that in such a Hazardous Time, <hi>cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet privato licet agere causam publicam,</hi> when it touches
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54203:3"/> on no Fundamental Constitutions, nor offers any Distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance herein: And as there is none but hath some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Interest in the Publick; so is he accountable by a Just Right to the Service thereof; <hi>&amp; in extremo dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimine unusquisque est miles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's sure an Advantage, when the sense of any Hazardous Case, whether it respects the Publick, or Mens Personal State, doth neither exceed nor fall short of the true grounds thereof: But this appears now to be a Time, when there may be more fear of a Deficiency, than Excess, on such an account; and Danger is oft nearest, when it is least apprehended. It is certain, that some Times have a more strange and extraordinary Aspect on the Publick State of a Nation, than may be in the ordinary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urse of things, or than useth to precede some great Vicissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes; and it's such in this Age, that the State of <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> hath been a Theatre of such Amazing Concussions and Changes, as no History past can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar a Resemblance thereto, in such Surprizing Var<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>us Scenes as have been Acted therein; nor can any suitable Reflection be on the same, without Admiration, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is day, how these Nations have not been swallowed up, and got safe out of all these Civil Storms that have sucees<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively followed each other; but yet with respect thereto, there seems to be such a present Juncture and Period now in the Publick State of Affairs, as exceeds all that's past, and a Time that speaks he <hi>Crisis</hi> to be in the very highest <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of its Conflict betwixt. Nature and the Disease, either to Life or Death: When the Wisest Pilots found it never more difficult to stear an even and safe Course betwixt Rocks and Quick-sands, when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass is like to fail, and is so difficult either to keep or gain ground against a cross Wind and Tide; when the Present State of things is a Sea of many Currents, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54203:3"/> do at once meet together. There is usually a growing Decay by the Distempers of the Politick Body, as well as of the Natural, which hath an inevitable Progress, to the Dissolution thereof, if not timely prevented, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it prove too late to overcome the strength of the Disease. But there are two things this day which may be sadly apprehended, as to the Consequences thereof; one is, to what a height Intestine Distempers in the Present State of <hi>Brittain</hi> are come; which have their Time of Breeding as well as of Breaking forth; and, when not regarded, use not to Dissolve without a new Storm; yea, have a most sad and mortal Aspect, when they prove so Incurable as to despise all Moral Relief, or any Restraint; from that Advantage the Publick Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary gets hereby; when it's more easie to make a Breach, than to stand up therein, against Visible Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard; or to Sacrifize Private Resentments to the Interest and Safety of their Countrey. But there is another Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard which may be too justly fear'd herewith, of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion and Falling off of many from the Publick State, either by Prejudices and Discontent, or an Indifference and Irresoluteness to fix, until they see a further Decision, and to know the way to be safe. It's true, that Men of the choicest Spirit, in a Time of Commotions, to avoid the Scene and Disturbances of a Troubled Time, and with respect to the Calm and Serenity of their own Mind, may find it desirable to retire, and be abstract from the Hurryings that are abroad, which cannot be strange or mistaken, if it shuts out no Duty, nor Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for their Countries Interest and Safety; but it must be a Stretch above an ordinary Reason and Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if such as are Protestants, and truly interested in the Rights and Liberties of the Nation, can have a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Interest from the same, or project to themseves
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54203:4"/> another Port to put in at, for Publick Security, or fix on any ground else, if they should fall off from this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorage. It is the End that determines the Means, and the Intenseness of Mens Spirits thereon, that tends to a Resolute and Unwearied Endeavour for Attaining the same, to have things brought on unto a steady Issue; but now, when it bears such clear Evidence, to be both <hi>pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> either to do or die; it's then that Reason and Necessity leave no room for a Faint, or a Suspence herein.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more suitable in the way of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, than for such as have a more Immediate Call and Interest than others, to enquire into the Natural Springs of such cross Events and Difficulties, that may not be easie to comprehend in an ordinary way, as they come under Humane Management; and which does then vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly tend to lay a dead Weight on Publick Actings, and cause their Motions to drive heavily; since otherwise the greatest Advantage of Strength, should be little avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, without such Measures of Wisdom, as to direct and apply the same to its proper End: But it is sure in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is Reason more highly Exerted for a Nation's Safety, than on this Principle of Eternal Truth, that no State can be safe with any Advantage of Means, if it be not under a Divine Conduct and Protection, that thus growing Difficulties and Disappointments might be traced to a higher Issue, than Visible Causes, as under a deep Sense and Impression of this, that God hath not forsaken the Earth. No Despondent Fear of Events should at any time weaken Mens hands in the Work of their Day, or take them off from present Duty; yea, were there the most clear and predictive Evidences of an Imminent Stroak and Ruin, yet might it not shut out the highest Efforts both of Counsel and Strength,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54203:4"/> for a Peoples Preservation: And as God does determine the End by Infallible Predestination; so does he move also by Inferior Causes and Means; for which he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Men accountable, as to the utmost Improvement hereof, both for their Safety and Success: Yet hath this ever been in the procedure of Providence remarkable, that before any Great and Extraordinary Events, both as to Kingdoms and Cities, there have been then more reamrkably than at other times, Monitory Signs and Warnings, which as Heraulds, were directed with a proper Commission and Authority, to awaken Men to their Duty. And as it is one of the great Demonstrations of a Deity; so does it ever witness the tender Respect of the Divine Majesty to Humane Race, and the Work of his own hand; and the Condecency of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both to the Excellencies of his own Nature, and Constitutions of his Word; but if any such Immediate Appearances of God, be not then suitably regarded, and operative by a Moral Influence on Mens Spirits, it may be a too evident Presage that things are hastening to some sad and determinate Ruine, by an unpreventable Providence, which I fervently desire may not be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to this Time.</p>
            <p>As to what is peculiarly designed in this following Discourse, it is to offer some Thoughts in a Rational View and Prospect of the Present State we are in, and what manner of Time it is, with respect to the Publick Concerns and Security of <hi>Brittain,</hi> as it respects Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible Causes hereof: For as no Sign is more promising, than, when the Things of the Day are specially regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the proper Season thereof, answerable to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences that are Depenednt on the same: So is the Voice of Reason, in its True and Regular Exercise as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly the Voice of God both to Nations and Persons.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54203:5"/> And, I hope, such an Address as this, may not be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken, when it demands no further Regard from any, than the Evidence and Truth of what's here offer'd, does make way for.</p>
            <p>1. It is unquestionable, that the first Entry of a Cure, must be in discerning the Cause and Nature of the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease; and that in no Case this is more called for, than with respect to Publick Hazard at a distance: That a due sight and sense hereof, must go before Prevention of the same, e're it be too late. It is a Proposal that may be now justly made; if <hi>England,</hi> with the other two Nations, be not stated in such a Conjunction, upon its Future Safety and Preservation, as seems to have no Parallel from former Presidents, to answer such a Case. It is indeed placed, as a World by it self, which is lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally divided from the whole Earth beside: But this cannot secure it from any Remarkable Hazard within, or that easie Access may be thus given to a Forraign Power and Design. What Men see with their Eyes, and is matter of Ocular Demonstration, can be no dark Problem now, that it is not the <hi>French</hi> Power alone, in its most strenuous workings; or any hid Design of an Intestine Party, that's to be fear'd this Day, in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Capacities; but the Joynt-Interest of both, in such a Correspondence: and under these Circumstances things are now stated, as hath not been formerly known; and when Hazard in such gradual and near Approaches, hath so remarkable an Aspect, it may need both a piercing Eye and Intelligence to prevent a Surprize that may not find us asleep. It is such a Day, when an Adversary at our Gates, and another within, seems to wait every Advantage, when both the <hi>French</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess and Strength, is at another pitch than hath been in Times past, whose Disposition and Intent lies so visibly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54203:5"/> for War, wherever with any favourable prospect they can open the same more than a Counterfeit Profession made for Peace: And so far may it be seen, if the Watching Eye of Providence do not interpose, that a Train is in some unusual manner laid, and working to its last Effort, more against <hi>Brittain,</hi> than any other Reformed State, as may need the utmost of Counsel and Resolution to countermine the same, before the springing thereof; when the loss of Time and Opportunity for such an End, seem'd never more Fatal if not suitably Improved; and it leaves no room to question that we are stated against such an Adversary, as is waiting every Advantage, and wants no Force or Conduct to manage the same; whose greatest Fear and Indignation does terminate upon <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the United Provinces this day, more than on any place else: But know, the Strength of such a Design lies in the Closeness thereof, to keep off any Unnecessary Discovery, and is not, as with some Labourers with their hands, who at every stroke give a groan: But what herewith should make the Prospect of such a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard more tremendous, is what may be fear'd of a too numerous Party, that lie as in Ambush, from within, to act a more Tragick and Bloody Scene in these Nations, if occasion did offer, than hath been ever known; as if they knew no other way to Rise but on a Publick Ruine, and could be Witnesses, without weeping at a Nations Funeral. I do not question but that many in this Day, may be too deeply engag'd in sad and cross Designs to the Present Settlements; as suppose to themselves a consistence herein with the Publick Safety, and that it should be only to change the Scene with new Actors therein. I confess if they fix the Conclusion before the Premises, and can judge by contraries, they may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count then such a thing might be supposable; but if they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54203:6"/> give Reason once leave to exercise second Thoughts, it cannot be conceivable to their own Judgment, that a new Overturning-could again take place, but that a most Bloody and Tragick Part should commence therewith; and that if ever the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Romish</hi> Power get up to the Bench, this Scene may then by unavoidable Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence be reckoned, as the Measure of their Acting; to have in the first place the Protestant Interest, with such as have any true Zeal or Value for the same, pay the Expence for all that is past, and stand as Criminal at the Bar: And if it should not be easie to turn the same wholly off the Stage, yet to have it stand alone, and be reduced to its Primitive State, to subsist without Humane Support or Countenance, so as it may serve, as <hi>Sampson,</hi> for its Adversaries Triumph; when without fear that even then it may pull down the House upon them: But the next step to follow hereon, by too evident a Result, is to be once Avenged of that great Supporter of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Rights and Liberties, which hath so long stood in their way, and still break their Measures, when they seemed most secure herein; but what herewith is more than supposable, would be their greatest Strength, and with some favourable Pretence lie here, to serve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of one part of the Nation, as Friends, to destroy the other, until the whole be render'd utterly uncapable of Self-defence, that it might at last be made a Publick Sacrifice to Implacable Revenge: When such then as have been made serviceable to so great a Ruine, should know how dear a Purchase a late Repentance is; to have seen themselves thus run on their own Swords by a Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Assassination, and involved thus their Children, and dear Relations in Publick and Irrevocable Ruine. But when I now write this, it is, I may say, with Abhorrence of unsuitable Reflection on the Persons of any, as might
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54203:6"/> in the least prejudge Justice and Truth, or to stretch the Designs of the greatest Adversaries, beyond what Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial and Just Reason makes unavoidable: But I must oppose the clearest Prospects of Sense and Reason, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less I see that any Destructive Opposition to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Publick Settlements this Day, if it did prevail, should be such as in the Issue and Consequences thereof, might make them become a Terrour to themselves, who should be Actors therein, and do not apprehend where such a Tyde might carry beyond their present Intent.</p>
            <p>2. It may be thus clear and demonstrable to unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged Reason, that never was a greater Cause brought upon the Stage, as to an Eventual Determination, than in the Present State of this War, as is now stated against <hi>France,</hi> which both its Justice and Necessity hath made so unavoidable: Yea, that a higher Interest did never lie at the Stake, with respect to the Reformed Churches, than at this Day; as cannot but raise Extraordinary Thoughts upon the Issue of such a Scene, wherein these Principal Concerns, both as we are Men and Christians, are so nearly interested. What may be the <hi>French</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs in such a Time, needs not in this respect a deep Scrutiny, when the Measure thereof may be so clearly judged by the Height and Measure of their Power, and where to this are set no Bounds: It's no Moral Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from Justice and Equity can be expected, to give a Restraint thereto, or make a Peace or Settlement safe for any, who are not upon an equal Foot, to secure the Violation thereof. And as for the Honour and Publick Faith of <hi>France,</hi> neither will that be sufficient to secure a Peace, tho' it should be laid in Pledge, more than the Punick Faith was of old; since that Kings way, not only to the <hi>French</hi> Protestants, but to the Princes of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:54203:7"/> Catholick Religion, hath given too certain a Trial, that his Claim of Right is of the same Extent as his Sword can make it, which hath been hitherto the Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Judge thereof; so as the Adjacent Princes have at last found it more safe to have him for an Adversary than a Friend. It was once Queen <hi>Elizabeth's Motto, No Peace with Spain,</hi> which could not be justisiable, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such grounds and necessity as are now more demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strable in this present Case: For War is undoubtedly to be reckoned the highest Act of Vindictive Justice, both upon Necessary Defence, and for Prevention of Imminent Hazard. It cannot be denied but that this Year 93. hath given a new Testimony before the World to the Repute and Honour of the King, both of the greatness on an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Courage, and Wise Conduct amidst Extraordinary Difficulties and Oppositions: And that if the Spirit of this great Prince had not some remarkable Ascendant on the present Adversary, his Motions probably might have been directed to much higher Attempts, and gone beyond all Bounds; but it may be seen likewise, that the Events of this Year, call for some Extraordinary Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the same. And in the first place, to a more abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Settling of our Dependencies on God: But as things lie under Humane Management, there may be a further Call to see that it will not be easie to keep ground, or avoid some remarkable Loss of the same, if it be not with that Strenuous and United Assistance followed, as under Divine Conduct may bring things to some desirable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision; since Attempts otherwise might prove as the forcing a great Stone up a Hill, that upon any faint, or slackning of Strength, goes a greater way back. And it's easie to judge, that any new Success, or Advantage the <hi>French</hi> do gain, carries them to take new Measures and Resolutions, as their way thus is prepared. It is not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54203:7"/> questionable, but that each Passenger in the Vessel, when a Storm riseth, hath the same proper Interest and Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture in its Safety, when it's like to perish. All's well as the common Concern of all therein is necessarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged. No Station is so low where Men are not stated in some capacity to act for the Interest of their Countrey, tho' all have not the same Room and Trust herein: And the greater Difficulties that Publick Services are beset with, it will ever tender to render the Issue more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and such a Reward to its self, as exceeds the lower Motives, with Men of a truly Publick Spirit. There's an undoubted Circulation in the Politick Body as well as in the Natural; so as Services done and design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the same, in an Extream Case, will return with some Signal Advantage and Reward of Honour, to them or theirs, tho' for many days it should not appear so. It hath no less appeared in the Issue, how sad and fatal a Prudence it was, that hath divided such from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Interest of their Countrey and People, to avoid Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, and to be thus unresolved where to fix, until the Ballance be cast to some absolute Decision, as such who are only determined by Events, but not by Principles.</p>
            <p>3. It is certain that things can have no true Rest or Settlement but in their proper Center, which must other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise move in a perplex and uncertain Agitation, which is ever no less evident in the Politick Body of a Kingdom and State, than in the Constitutions of Nature, that it must have a Central and Uniting Interest, whereby the Stability of the whole Frame, is sixt, and its Motions rendered steady and concentrick with the same. It's hereby that both the Security of Sacred and Civil Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests, is settled on such sure ground, as may take off Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, or Distrust of such cross and extrinsick Motions that may prove destructive thereto, It is surely accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54203:8"/> to this, that the Publick Safety and Interest of <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> this Day must be rationally judged, when it bears such a prevailing Influence on Mens Spirits; as to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate all Inferiour Designs and Counsels thereunto, and to Interest them against whatever tends to break such a Conjunction: For it's not the strongest Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Law, or of a Servile Fear thereof, that will bind, if these Ligaments of Love and of Mutual Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in a way of Trust and Assurance, should be once broke, and the Contracted Interest of a Party takes off that Propension and Respect, that should be to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick State of the Body; which without Prophecy may presage some great Ruine to be then impendent; when instead of Mutual Trust, private Enmities and cross Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings take the room thereof, and goes above any Relief. And with respect to this, I hope it cannot be questioned what by the highest Reason is so demonstrable; in what relation both Their Majesties now upon the Throne of <hi>Brittain</hi> stand, as to the Present Safety of these Nations and Future Security; and what an Interest they carry in their hand on such an account, so as this Bond of Union cannot possibly be slacked, or made void, without subverting the Foundations of the whole Frame, and a Fatal Dissolution of the same. The firmest Settlement of Government proves oft too weak to support, when an intire Settlement of Mens Spirits keeps not foot there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and a sense of their own Interest and Security un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the same, to Influence an Uniting Temper in the common Cause. It should be strange if the State where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>England</hi> was a few Years past, be not to this Day kept in sight, and these sad Depressions and Terrours on Mens Spirits, which did hold them under so visible a Bondage, when it was valued at so high a rate, to be once again Witness to such a Time, when Law and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54203:8"/> Justice should be Settled and Certain Measures of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as is this Day. It is not questionable but that Private Losses must deeply affect Mens Spirits, and have a just Sense thereof, wherein the Publick Interest does also suffer; but it should be a Direful Effect, to alienate thus from the Government, upon the Miscarrying of any Inferiour Instruments, or to reckon their Conditions could be bettered by a Change; as in the Fable of the Froggs, who could not be satisfied until they at last got such a Prince and Ruler, whose Power was only extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to devour them. It is a Blessing rarely given a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to have such at the Helm in a Tempestuous Time, whose Interest all may see indissolubly conjoyn'd with the Publick, and ready to Sacrifice his nearest Concerns, on that Altar of the Nations Safety and Preservation, whose Religion is one and the same with theirs, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued both with true Greatness of Mind, and a Judicious Prudence to grapple with growing Hazards. It is known how the Protestant State of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> did rise, and prevail against so Potent a Force, as was then against them, which next to Divine Assistance, was by being so harmoniously unite, and spirited by the common Love of their Religion, Countrey and Liberties, and by what entire confidence they had in that Illustrious House of <hi>Orange,</hi> who were the alone great Instruments to raise and deliver the same: And as by a Divine Destination Prince <hi>William,</hi> whose Memory is so famous to the World, did lay his whole Interest at the Stake to raise and deliver the same, when almost swallowed up by an Arbitrary Power: So now by a most singular Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath the Security and Restauration of <hi>England</hi> with the other two Kingdoms from such Imminent Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard terminated in this great Prince, and hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served for him; which is an Honour, with respect to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54203:9"/> that Illustrious House in a successive Line, to be such Eminent Patriots, both as to Sacred and Civil Rights, that hath rarely occurred in the course of Humane Affairs to any Princes, or Family in the World, and is a remark of such an Extraordinary Providence, as cannot be easily past.</p>
            <p>4. It is surely a great Advantage, when in a Time of Publick Danger there is a true Estimate and Judgment made of a Nations Intrinsick Strength, which in a Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane way, is the alone stable, and permanent Interest thereof, by which they can understand the true Measure both of their Fears and Hope on such an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and may be thus secured from a Fatal Mistake, in any Extraordinary Case. I know the numerous En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease and Growth of a People, is truly an Evidence of growing Strength; but yet this does not always hold, or can be judged by Number or Poll, since the more spread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Community may be of a Nation, the more sad Aspect it hath, if a degenerate Race should get up, where the prevalency of Debauchery and Immorality, does so naturally tend to depress the Genius of a People, and the pursuance of any Honourable Ends; yea strikes at the Root of all Civil and Moral Duties, where the true Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of a Government lies. Nor does a Kingdoms Strength from within it self, lie in the Measure of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Preparations for the Publick Safety (the most ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely necessary) so much as in the Interiour Spring both of Resolution and Integrity herewith, to put these agoing in their due order and place, as <hi>Solomon</hi> speaks, that there needs more Strength to be added, if the Iron be blunt; yet Wisdom alone is profitable to direct, as the Leading Principle of all Exterior Motions: And it may be seen what a prevalence the Spirit of some, when it is of a higher Elevation and Capacity than in others, will have to actuate and enliven a multitude to such Services,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54203:9"/> as may be above their ordinary Reach, which is usually one of the most promising Signs to a Kingdom, when such are in any singular way then raised with some pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar excellency of Spirit, for the work of that Time.</p>
            <p>But as to what might be most conducible for such an End to secure and promote the Interest of <hi>Brittain,</hi> in its true, stable, and permanent Strength from within it self, and to have a right Prospect thereof, I do not pretend to judge; this being a Subject proper and suitable to such under whose hand the Directing and Governing Power lies, and stand related as Eyes to the Nation to watch for its Safety; yea when so much may be justly in this Day expected from these; only with a humble and due distance, I shall adventure to point at some things in distinct way, that I hope will not come under que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, to be most nearly related to this great End.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it's both the Glory and Strength of a Nation in sad and hazardous Times, to have an open Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Fear and Dependance on God, kept upon the Face of all Publick Actings; of him under whose hands, the Government and Dominion of the World does absolutely stand, and who alone is the Protector of Nations; since Reason cannot possibly find another way to be safe upon any Temporal Interest, or for Mens being true to themselves, but in the Truth and Serious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Religion; so as in the greatest Exigence these can never be distinguisht, what is just, and what is safe, being Convertible Terms. But it's on this Subject, I have been oft put to some astonishing Thoughts, how Religion should have so great an Influence to turn about the Publick Affairs and Concerns of the World, and this way to have much Rule over the Actions of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life, when it hath so small a Vital Influence on Mens Minds, in order to the higest Ends thereof, and for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54203:10"/> an Eternal Interest, when it goes thus no further, than an empty and unlivened Form; yea to see with what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenseness Names of discrimination are stated on such an account.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is of undoubted Evidence likewise that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Reformed Religion, which is the pure and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Truth of Christianity, is the Strength and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Interest of <hi>England,</hi> and both the other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms this Day: This needs no Evidence of Conviction to such for a close Adherence to the same, who are too wise and sensible of their own Safety, to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves again under the Popish Yoke, after so dear and Expensive a Trial hath been hereof; or that in a Time of such Light, it could be possible upon Choice to give up their Reason and Judgment unto others, by an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Trust, and not see with their own Eyes; but to account a Blind Obedience one of the great Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of their Faith; yea when there can be no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding here, where so Impassable a Gulf is fixt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt these two Professions. But the things pertaining to the Conscience, and of the highest Publick Interest, should have a small regard, as may be judged with too many: Yet is there a concern of another nature to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence in this case; that if ever Popery should be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to pursue its Antient Title and Inheritance, then a numerous Party of the most Eminent Families in these Nations, might be in hazard to have theirs swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up hereby, whatever pretences may for a time be made otherwise: Yea, that if it once got on Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, they might be then put to walk on foot; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of such a Religion be made to Sacrifize the Hearth unto the Altar; who upon more high and noble grounds, were not suitably excited, to withstand the first Invasions thereof, and to have this great End
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54203:10"/> with respect to Divine Truth made theirs: And if things past may be Prognosticks of future, it is known what Breaches the <hi>French</hi> Power hath of late made, not only on Mens Rights and Civil Soceity; but on Humanity it self, as in the Palatinate and other Adjacent places; and in such measures of Cruelty, as was acted against the Protestants in <hi>France,</hi> which was with the highest Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the Law of Gratitude towards these, whose Ancestors were so Assistant to bring the House of <hi>Bourben</hi> to the Throne, and stem that Tyde of the Catholick League, which was against the same: But if a Just Reflection be made also, on what may lie yet nearer to us, for Eviction of this, it might be easie to see, how different the state of things, from what was in the Year Eighty Eight, is this Day, upon the most va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Interest and Security of such a nature which Men possibly can enjoy, whereby a Title to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligon, Lives, and Liberties, hath not got a Legal hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without fear of any Designed Violation of the same by Force.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is unquestionable also, that where a People is in the way of their Strength, and under propitious Influences from Heaven for their Security, that some remarkable Gale of Counsel and Prudence, useth then to go along therewith; and in seasonable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of the same to the present Day: Yea that the Measure of a Nations Strength in a Humane way, may be accordingly thus judged to know, both what is to be done, and what is to be avoided, to see and foresee things that may lie remote from the Ordinary Judgment of many, both as to the tendency of Hazard, and preparations thereto, and from what point a Storm may be near to break up. It's true, the most knowing and judicious, that watch for their Conntries Safety,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54203:11"/> may meet ost with Surprizing Accidents, that then seem'd not supposable to them: But it is known like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise what Improvements of Reason and Counsel, have in a most singular way been attain'd, when Difficulties and Hazards have gone above any ordinary Judgment herein: It's in this respect, there is such a Divination of Judicious Prudence for prevention of Hazard, as may be called Natural Prophecy, though it have a Divine Rise and Original, and is given to a People as one of the most Eminent Blessings from Heaven: Yea verifies that Sacred Truth, how Wisdom is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrable to Strength, and strengtheneth the Wise, more than Ten Mighty Men, that are in the City. But on this Subject I need speak little, when so much this Day may be justly hoped for, from the Wisdom of Publick Counsels, and such Experienced Pilots that are at the Helm in so Threatning a Storm, who know in this present Conjunction, how to have such a Scheme of Prevention judiciously settled, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to Visible Hazard, as may not leave the same to a Surprize, upon any sudden Emergents, or for taking Counsel too late. It hath been hitherto the Result of most Deliberate Counsels, to meet Publick Hazard at a distance, rather than wait for its nearer Approach; when otherwise it seems more than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural, where so high a Flight of the <hi>French</hi> Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Power, should have come e're now without such a prevalent Stop; and may be yet judged, that since a Design was never more working than is this Day, how to try their Strength on British ground, if their Will and their Power were commensurate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It surely may be a special Indication also of the Standing Interest and Strength of <hi>Brittain</hi> from within, in such a Time as this, by what Advantage is gain'd, to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54203:11"/> have the Publick Government, so far as is possible, rooted in the general Affection and Esteem of the People; and that Mutual Confidence and Trust fixed, which is the Life and Sinews of Government, and all Humane Society, so as by a constraint of Reason, they can see, how the King and the Nation this Day, are so nearly Conjoyn'd and Stated in that Relation, as to be the Mutual Interest and Safety of other; and how his Just Greatness and Rights, with the whole Legal Freedom and Liberties of the People, are so joyntly founded on the same Basis, as to beget an entire Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiescence of Mind herein; and how thus the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is sure and adequate to the Structure that rests thereon; so that not by Fear, or on the Influence of an Imperative Power, but by an Elicite Choice from Love and Esteem the Government may be Establisht, and that Homage due to the Soveraign, be given, not by the Knee alone, but by the Heart. It can come under no question in what Posture the State of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was in, before this late Revolution, and what Mortal Signs then was, of some great Ruine to be near, when the Government was like to become more <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Italian,</hi> than <hi>English;</hi> and the Late King so far engag'd to Espouse a Party instead of the Publick Body, by joyning in with the <hi>Romish</hi> Counsels and Power to promote that Interest, as he had so far past the Rubicon, in what was so visibly cross to the Establisht Laws and Constitutions of the Nation: But as this is too late to be forgot; so it is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable by any Humane Rise, that in another way the Publick State this Day can be preserved, than in the same way wherein, by so Extraordinary a Destina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Providence it was attained; and I judge, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54203:12"/> none of a Considerate Spirit can suppose any Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive Design to the Publick Settlements, should take place, but by so Bloody a Scene, as no Humane Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief could stop it, in the way of Reason, until it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd in the Dismal and Tragick Effects. It is true, the private Burthens of many in these Times, may be very pungent and sore, which they who look at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance thereon, do too little regard; but when the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Safety is at the Stake, and evident, at how dear a Rate there would be Compounding of the same, if Adversaries got further Advantage; it cannot but have a Ballancing Weight, on Mens Spirits, when they see, how all that can be Valuable to them within Time, is conjoyn'd therewith.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though the Extensive Interest of <hi>Brittain,</hi> in its present Increase, is such, that it may be said to be, as the Sand of the Sea in number; yet since the True and Intrinsick Strength of a People, does ever respect the Quality, more than the Bulk and Extent thereof; it cannot be otherwise understood in this Day, or a true Measure of our Hope on this account, but by such a promising and true Growth of these who are Acted on some higher Account than their private Concerns, to joyn their Interest with the Publick, in a Time of Hazard, and not from a low and servile Spirit in this matter; who have such a Sense both of Religion and Honour, as to render them True to any Publick Trust they are in, and does seek no otherwise but in the way of Services and Just Merit to have an Intrinsick Interest in the Affection and Esteem of their Countrey; who account the Reward of being Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Publick Interest, a Compensation for any Trouble or Loss they can sustain hereby, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54203:12"/> holds no Repute from Ostentation of the same, since any true Excellency and Worth, even amongst the worst of Men, hath such an Interest in Humane Nature, as they cannot possibly deny some hid Veneration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nor forego a just sense hereof, even where Enmity and Envy is prevalent: And it's indeed one of the most high and desirable Ends that Men can attain in their Day, to have done or designed something in a more than ordinary way, for the present Generation, and their Countries Interest in a Hazardous Time: Yea this does render the same, more highly comforting and honourable, as a Service of this kind, hath been beset with greater Difficulties and Opposition than usual. But when I touch this, there's something that cannot be disjoyn'd from it, to advance thus the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and Strength of a Nation, from within it self, and of great use for this End, which is in a suitable Retribution of Reward and Favour from the Publick to any just Merit, which hath a special tendency to give Encouragement and Life to Honourable Acts and Attempts; yea, to take off Resentments that might be occasioned by any unaccountable Ingratitude, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> observes; and does too usually occur in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Humane Affairs, that a poor wise Man, (as is there shewed) helpt by his Wisdom to save a City, yet no Man did regard him herein: It is known from the History of all Times, how Instruments and Means, are remarkably rais'd and acted forth, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Designs of Providence about such a place; but where it is known aright, it may then give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly a Signal Prognostick upon a Nations standing or falling. But it comes upon the same Concern, to have some equal Respect also, and a suitable Resent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54203:13"/> of any sinistrous and cross Actings, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Interest; so as it may with a special note ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that there is no way for Men, either to secure their Credit, or private Concerns upon any special Trust, by being unfaithful to the Publick; and that such must stand or fall this way, by their Integrity herein. It is true, it may oft be Mens Lot to be unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate and not false; and things managed with the most sincere Design, and without any Deficiency ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Courage or Wisdom, falls under great Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments and Cross Events; but this rarely wants such Evidence, as may justifie the same, to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of all unprejudiced, and secure from all unjust grounds of suffering hereby.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But there is a Concern of another nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Standing and Strength of a Nation is especially interested, and seem'd never more applicable than now, to the State of <hi>Brittain;</hi> to have such a Temper settled in a Dividing Time, and amids these numerous Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, amongst the most serious Protestants, as may not in Extream Hazard, obstruct an Unite Acting for the Publick Interest, or divide the Nations Strength from it self. It's true, there can be no possible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement, on a Politick Account, of Light and Darkness; nor can Truth and Errour ever have a coali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or be compounded, or admit any Indifference about things of Sacred Concern: But on the other hand it's evident, that the Rearing up of Walls of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, this way, have a strange and dismal Aspect; so far as they tend to shut out Friends from any harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Concurrence to the Publick Safety, and gives any Strength to the Adversary to enter thereby. I know that Mens Reason and Judgment are not in their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54203:13"/> own power to dispose of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lieve what they please, no more, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in the most natural Acts of their Life, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ictive Evidence, that such as are under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> must have their Perswasion and Light determined; nor is it suppos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to find any huma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Society, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of Sacred or Civil Constitution, that will not be under some diversity of Light and Judgment, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this can give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Union <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Safety, or to stand together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> when i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is in some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> than ordinan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well that it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Subject of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Prudence of these who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Nation, can so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> how to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> this should have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Rule, since <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is founded in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> so in their Subserviency <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Publi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Interest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the whole Body, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for, in some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Interest, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Support <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ublick Necessary Defence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are unquestionably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Religion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54203:14"/> Standing, so closely imbarqued therewith, as to be Vouchers for their Fidelity, in their being capacitated for the same; and who by a Natural Right stands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the Politick Body, as Citizens and Members thereof, and may have a considerable Influence to promote a common Interest, though in some things more remote from the same, there be a difference in Light and Judgment.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But I must yet adventure on such a Subject, to touch one particular more, that may possibly seem incongruous with what does precede; and when things of another nature takes now up the Spirits of most as to the Publick Security of the Nation; that is too clear, when seriously pondered, will be found to have a most near and indissoluble connection therewith; that since it's sure the true and permanent Interest of <hi>Brittain,</hi> does stand by the Truth and Stability of Religion, and as it's now fixt in the purest Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession there, by an Unchangeable Rule; it must be then equal to judge, that the most Eminent Hazard and Weakning of the Publick State, does lie in the most destructive and prevalent Opposition to such an Interest, when it is as the Scales in the Ballance, where the Rise of the one▪ is the Depression of the other. It is on this Head that from a sad and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistable Reflection; I cannot but see and refer it to the Reason and Judgment of all, what shall be the Issue of the Protestant Profession this Day, and how dismal and dark a night is like to fall down on these Nations, and on the Politick Interest thereof, if this Modern and Improved Atheism of these late Times, shall get further Strength, and make a New Conquest proportionably to what hath been in some Years
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54203:14"/> past, and where it is like to stand when its Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches are so strange, as with pretences to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, to strike at the whole Interest and Foundations of Revealed Religion; for without some more than Ordinary Design and Care for prevention of the same, it is not like to resolve so much, in a Regress to Popery (though it gains thus a special Strength by the Inconsistencies of such a way, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Reason, or with it self) but in a Visible Apostacy from the Christian Faith, that this Day may be most feared. It is unquestionable that this World and Humane Race and Society therein, could not Morally subsist as to any Order, Justice and Security amongst Men, without the Faith and Impressions of a Deity to bear out the same; nor could the Earth be possibly Habitable or Safe to Live therein, if the Sense of Religion, and Fear of an Invisible God, were not Implanted in him and Nature: But it's sure this must needs be more specially applicable to a Kingdom and People, which hath entred with greater Light and Engagements on so high and discriminating a Profession of Christianity, beyond most of the Earth; and that the Spreading Encrease of such a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion, and the Standing of a Nation in its Politick Interest and Concerns, will be found so incompatible, as that a Publick Ruine is then at hand. It was a just Saying of one of the Antients, on such an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>Si tibi non vis parcere, attamen parce Patriae tuae;</hi> and it was from so sad a prospect of this, that of late Mr. <hi>Robert Boyle</hi> (who was so great an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, both to his Countrey, and Profession, as a Christian) did make it his last Design, to have some further Improvement made against so Mortal and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54203:15"/> Growing a Contagion, by Settling a Fund for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a Publick Lecture, which he committed to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Trustees for making it Effectual, that might on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be directed to such an End: Yea what a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Presage should it be this Day, if a Project of such a nature as this, might prove more exemplary, and to find Mens Spirits set more on such high and truly generous Designs, for the present and future Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration? We know in what manner the Zeal of the Romish Church, did carry them for that End, <hi>de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paganda Fide,</hi> so as to have a proper Settlement and Society Erected and set apart wholly in this respect, which should have been a most rare Undertaking, if it had not visibly Counter-acted such a Profession; yet is such an Example, as may be a Publick Witness, against the Indifference of the Reformed Churches, every where, too visible in this Case; and why there is not something in a more than ordinary way design'd, for the Defence of the Gospel, when it was never more put on a Defensive part, than now; and that all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Evidence of the Truth and Divinity thereof, on Mens Spirits, is so much lost. If there were a considerable part of the Nation that profest Heathenism, it might be judg'd this would take with Men of Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Controversies and Contendings, in behalf of the Christian Interest, and that their Strength would go forth this way; but is the Hazard less now, when the whole Revelation of Sacred Truth is in the Day-light attaqued, by so numerous a Party; and when on the other hand it is so visible, how most who bear the Christian Name are destitute of any Defence of their Profession, from Internal Motives, or Perswasion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, from its own Evidence? I do not question but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54203:15"/> that under such a Magistracy and Government, as is this Day settled in <hi>Brittain,</hi> but under a Prospect of such Hazard, they clearly see and discern that the Standing Interest and Security of the Nation, and the Safety of Religion, are of the same Extent, and must assuredly stand or fall together. But since it's the Youth, and Growing Race, wherein the Hope of a Nation does most specially lie, who seems to be now under the Saddest Influence of such a Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gion, and to be most susceptable thereof, yea these whose Quality may have a more Leading Influence than ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, and by whom the Publick Interest doth so much stand; it may be thus evident, that the most Adequate Mean for Prevention, and to answer such an End, does most peculiarly lie in the Publick Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries and Universities, where the Reformed Religion is profest. It is true, that there is no Deficiency there, as to the furthest Improvement of the Noetick part of Divinity, and insisting on Modern Controversies, but rather to the Excess herein: But I must profess it as matter of Astonishment, that in such an Age the Drao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick part hereof is not more intensly followed and improved; so that the Youth which are coming for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, both for Sacred, and Civil Imployments, might be thus engaged to see with their own Eyes the Truth and Firmness of these Principles whereon their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession is settled, and with such clearness of Demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Evidence, as the great Author of our Religion hath so abundantly given for this Intent: It will be questioned by none, that the Natural Order of things does ever require the Foundation to be surely laid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Superstructure be rais'd: But as there is no want this Day to these who are most Eminently fitted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54203:16"/> to answer such a Design, nor any Defect of Conviction of the Necessity hereof, why this is not more follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a Work by it self, and as a Province that's ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the greatest Improvements; I must humbly judge, that this hath a special and too evident a Rise from this one Cause, that there is not a proper and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct Settlement entirely on such a Design, as well as there is for any other Profession, so as this might be peculiarly followed: And it might be thus judg'd, what a face and stamp it might put, by a Divine Concurrence therewith, on the Spirits of Men, and of these who are now the Hope of the Succeeding Race, when in so Inquisitive an Age there should be some higher Excitement this way; and when so many of late have been in an unusual manner carried out on that Choice Study, to know the true Phoenomina of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the proper Causes and Original of things, that there might herewith be some answerable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, and propension on a much higher account, to know these strong and firm Conveyances of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Faith, with the certainty of its own Evidence; and how no Natural Science can pretend to more clear and unanswerable Demonstrations, than the Truth of Supernatural Religion, in a rational and demonstrative way, to any considering Spirit. But since it is now on that ground, for which I especially touch this, upon such a Publick Interest, as the Standing and Safety of the Nation, hath so immediately therein, when Publick Hazard is otherways imminent; I hope, to these who are in a higher Capacity, both to judge, and be assistant, in such a case, that a Concern of this nature will be no Indifferent thing; and to see how great a National Interest this should make, that may be so effectual to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54203:16"/> promote the Moral part of Religion and Relative Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof, in a more Universal Diffusion of the same, and to take off that Brutish Credulity, which this Day is the Shame and Reproach of the Christian Profession; and which by a Native Result also should make way for higher Improvements, for the Establishment of Mens Spirits in the way of Truth; but which most specially also should have such a tendance to prepare and ripen a Ministry to the Church, who might be in a more peculiar way fitted to deal with Atheists and Infidels, and the greatest pretenders to Reason than hath been yet attained, by such Means as bear a most evident Congruity to Mens Natural Light and Reason, and to serve a Constraint thereon, so as to see that serious Religion must assuredly either be their Choice or their Torment: And how great a Service should this be to a National Interest and Flourishing, if this were more attain'd? Yea in a Time, when so numerous a part cannot be dealt with in another way, and take such Advantage for their prejudice and stumbling, when there is any want of a suitable Application of such Means.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:54203:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54203:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>